8                                              2 Input Language of cLING0

 parent (ann, bob) . parent (bob, carol) . parent (bob, dank
then what stable model do you think it will produce?             (2



2.1 Rules

As discussed in Sect. 1.2, a typical rule, such as (1.1) or (2.1), consists of a head
and a body separated by the "if" symbol : and with a period at the end. Rules (1.2)
and (2.2) do not contain "if"; such a rule is viewed as the head without a body.
   The heads and bodies of rules (1.1), (1.2) are formed from atoms

             large(C), size(C,S1), size(uk,S2),
             size(france,65), size(germany,83),
                  size(italy161), size(uk,64)

and one expression of another kind—a comparison, S1 > S2. Within an atom or
comparison, we see elements of three types: symbolic constants, numeric constants.
and variables. They can be distinguished by looking at the first character. A numeric
constant is an integer in decimal notation, so that its first character is a digit or
the minus sign. A symbolic constant is a string of letters, digits, and underscores
that begins with a lower-case letter. A variable is a string of letters, digits, and
underscores that begins with an upper-case letter.
   An atom consists of a predicate symbol-a symbolic constant representing
a property or a relation—and an optional list of arguments in parentheses. A
comparison consists of two arguments separated by one of the symbols



  Expressions that can serve as arguments in an atom or comparison are called
terms. The terms that we see in rules (1.1), (1.2), (2.1), (2.2) are constants and
variables, but in Sect. 2.3 we will encounter also complex terms that are formed
from constants and variables using arithmetic operations. In Sect. 7.5 we will talk
about one more way of forming terms—the use of symbolic functions.
  An atom, a rule, or another syntactic expression is ground if it does not contain
variables. We talked above about "facts" informally, now we can say that a rule is a
fact if it is a ground atom.
  In Sect. 1.3 we explained why CLINGO produces facts (1.3) in response to1
rules (1.1), (1.2) by saying that these are the facts that can be derived using these
rules. The first four of these facts are simply part of the program, but what about the
other two---in what sense can they be "derived"?
  This can be clarified by considering instances of rule (1.1)—the ground rules that
can be obtained from it by substituting constants for variables. The presence of the

